>> [clears throat] >> Comrades, you've heard already about the strange
dream that I had last night.
But I will come to the dream later.
I have something else to say first.
I do not think, comrades, that I shall be with you for many months longer. And
before I die, I feel it my duty to pass on to you such
wisdom as I have acquired.
I've had a long life.
I've had much time for thought as I lay alone in my stall,
and I think I may say that I understand the nature of life on this earth as well
as any animal now living.
It is about this that I wish to speak to you. Now, comrades, what is the nature
of this life of ours?
Let us face it.
Our lives are miserable, laborious, and short. We are born,
we are given just so much food as will keep the breath in our bodies,
and those of us who are capable of it are forced to work to the last atom of
our strength.
And the very instant that our usefulness has come to an end, we are slaughtered
with hideous cruelty.
No animal in England knows the meaning of happiness or leisure after he is a year old.
No animal in England is free.
The life of an animal is misery and slavery.
That is the plain truth.
But is this simply part of the order of nature?
Is it because this land of ours is so poor that it cannot afford a decent life
to those who dwell upon it?
No, comrades, a thousand times no!
The soil of England is fertile, its climate is good, it is capable of
affording food in abundance to an enormously greater number of animals than now inhabit it.
This single farm of ours would support a dozen horses, 20 cows, hundreds of
sheep, and all of them living in a comfort and a dignity that are now
almost beyond our imagining.
Why then do we continue in this miserable condition?
>> [clears throat] >> Because nearly the whole of the produce
of our labor is stolen from us by human beings.
There, comrades, is the answer to all our problems. It is summed up in a
single word, man. [clears throat] Man is the only real enemy we have.
Remove man from the scene and the root cause of hunger and overwork is abolished forever.
Man is the only creature that consumes without producing. He does not give
milk. He does not lay eggs. He is too weak to pull the plow. He cannot run
fast enough to catch rabbits.
Yet he is lord of all the animals. He sets them to work. He gives back to them
the bare minimum that will prevent them from starving and the rest he keeps for himself.
Our labor tills the soil. Our dung fertilizes it and yet there is not one
of us that owns more than his bare skin.
>> [clears throat] >> You cows that I see before me, how many
thousands of gallons of milk have you given during this last year?
And what has happened to that milk which should have been breeding up sturdy calves?
Every drop of it has gone down the throats of our enemies.
And you hens, how many eggs have you laid in this last year? And how many of
those eggs ever hatched into chickens?
The rest have all gone to market to bring in money for Jones and his men.
And you, Clover, where are those four foals you bore who should have been in
the support and pleasure of your old age?
Each was sold at a year old. You will never see one of them again.
>> [clears throat] >> In return for your four confinements and
all your labor in the fields, what have you ever had except your bare rations
and a stall? And even the miserable lives we lead are not allowed to reach their natural span.
For myself, I do not grumble, for I am one of the lucky ones.
I am 12 years old and have had over 400 children.
Such is the natural life of a pig.
But no animal escapes the cruel knife in the end.
You young porkers who are sitting in front of me, every one of you will
scream your lives out of the block within a year.
To that horror we all must come. Cows,
[clears throat]
pigs, hens, sheep, everyone.
Even the horses and the dogs have no better fate.
You Boxer, the very day that those great muscles of yours lose their power, Jones
will sell you to the who will cut your throat and boil you down for the foxhounds.
As for the dogs, when they grow old and toothless, Jones ties a brick round
their necks and drowns them in the nearest pond.
Is it not crystal clear then, comrades, that all the evils of this life of ours
spring from the tyranny of human beings?
Only get rid of man and the produce of our labor would be our own.
>> [clears throat] >> Almost overnight we could become rich and free.
What then must we do?
Why, work night and day, body and soul, for the overthrow of the human race.
That is my message to you, comrades, rebellion.
I do not know when that rebellion will come.
>> [clears throat] >> It might be in a week or in a hundred years.
But I know, as surely as I see this straw beneath my feet, that sooner or
later justice will be done.
Fix your eyes on that, comrades, throughout the short remainder of your lives.
And above all, pass on this message of mine to those who come after you, so
that future generations shall carry on the struggle until it is victorious.
And remember, comrades, your resolution must never falter.
No argument must lead you astray.
Never listen when they tell you that man and the animals have a common interest,
that the prosperity of the one is the prosperity of the others.
It is all lies.
Man serves the interests of no creature except himself. And among us animals,
let there be perfect unity, perfect comradeship in the struggle.
All men are enemies. All animals are comrades.
>> At this moment, there was a tremendous uproar.
While Major was speaking, four large rats had crept out of their holes and
were sitting on their hindquarters listening to him.
The dogs had suddenly caught sight of them, and it was only by a swift dash
for their holes that the rats saved their lives.
Major raised his trotter for silence.
>> Comrades, here is a point that must be settled.
The wild creatures, such as rats and rabbits, are they our friends or our enemies?
Let us put it to the vote.
I propose this question to the meeting.
Are rats comrades?
>> The vote was taken at once, and it was agreed by an overwhelming majority that
rats were comrades.
There were only four dissentients, the three dogs and the cat, who was
afterwards discovered to have voted on both sides.
Major continued.
>> I have little more to say.